Hey everyone, and thanks for jumping
back into the heavy metal verse.
Today, we're going to talk about gold
and discuss the low that it is trying to
seek out. If you guys like the content,
make sure you subscribe to the channel,
give the video a thumbs up, and also be
sure to get your ticket to the first
investing through the cycles conference
taking place in late November in Miami.
Link is in the description below.
Let's go ahead and jump in. So, gold is
now at 4,400. Now, if you guys remember
kind of throughout this year, what we've
sort of talked about was the idea that
2026 would be a reset year for gold,
that it would likely top early in the
year,
and then the rest of the year, most of
it would be a reset year,
but
that there's seasonality to when the
lows occur. So, take note of this.
The low, as it stands right now,
was in like late June, early July time
frame. Okay?
Now,
what's interesting about that
is if you look at the year-to-date RLI
of gold and look at the average of prior
midterm years going back to the 1970s,
what you'll see is that on average
there is a drop into the summer, and on
average the low is around July 6th.
Okay? So,
this time is more or less played out
like it normally does.
The only difference between this year
and the average of prior midterm years
is the volatility, right? I mean, the
average is somewhere over here, and gold
had a large remove to the upside, and
then it had a larger move to the
downside. But, you would expect the the
average to, you know, to obviously not
be at those extremes, and we can put one
standard deviation onto that average,
and you can kind of just see we went
above it, and then we went slightly
below it. But now, what you'll notice is
that gold started moving up
when it always does in the midterm year.
Now, some people might get hung up on
the fact that in 2022
and 2018, gold did not bottom until like
September-October timeframe. Okay, so
yes, it's possible that that could
happen. Okay, it is it Is it within the
realm of possibility that gold could put
a lower low in?
It's in the realm of possibility.
Be that as it may,
I don't necessarily know if that should
be the base case, right? If you look at
the gold bull market support band, which
is a which is made up of the 20-month uh
SMA and the 21-month EMA,
when we look at that,
what you'll notice is that we basically
bounced right off of it. I mean, we
didn't quite get there, but we got real
really, really close. And there are
plenty of bull markets in the past where
we would, you know, get close to it, but
not quite tag it.
Okay?
Now,
I previously have drawn the obvious
comparison, right? And I'm sure as
everyone goes to sleep at night, they're
probably thinking just how similar this
gold move has been to 1974, right? I
mean, obviously
we're on the same boat, right? Like
we're on the same boat there. And And
so, what happened in 1974
for gold is that it had
a big move up
off above the regression band, right?
And what ended up happening is it topped
in early 1974.
And it had a low
in the summer.
You see that? Now, we're going to zoom
in now.
But you can pretty clearly see it,
right? You had a a high in early 1974,
a low printed in the summer that was
above the bull market support band,
right?
We bounced,
found a local top in August,
and then a higher low
in September. Higher low. And what's
fascinating is that gold went on to put
in a new all-time high
before the end of the year. Now, I don't
want to go as far to say that that has
to happen. It doesn't. But, what I would
say
is if you look at this move,
we had almost a 30% drop,
and then gold bottomed in the summer,
and then had about a 50% rally before
the year was over.
Now, if you go look and and again, let's
actually zoom in a little bit on the
weekly because I'd like to show
where gold found that higher low. Like,
where what week it printed, right? So,
the week the higher low formed
was the week of September 23rd.
Okay? September 23rd.
The low was the week of July 1st. Like,
keep that in mind. The The low was the
week of July 1st.
The higher low was the week of September
23rd.
Now, when you go look at gold today,
the low
June The week of June June 29th.
Basically, the same week. Instead of
July 1st, it was the week of June 29th.
But, that would go into July.
Basically, the same week.
The higher low potentially forms
in a couple of weeks, maybe. Now, what's
interesting is that if a higher low were
to form,
I would suggest
that
it would bottom
before other markets would.
If you look at what happened in 1974,
while gold found the low, the higher low
in September,
the S&P, it was going through them. I
mean, we didn't have this AI massive
build-out, but there was this seasonal
weakness around that time. The S&P found
the low
uh kind of going into early October. It
was the week of September 30th, so it
was like a week a week or so after after
when gold did. So, and and then the S&P
still didn't go anywhere until the
following year, right? It went up, but
then came back down,
was still at those lows while gold was
at all-time highs.
So,
what I what I want you to think about
with this gold move
is what's happened this year
is really normal move for gold. All
right, this is absolutely
uh a a a fairly standard move. Gold
moves up at the beginning, it drops into
the summer, and then it bounces.
If you're looking at what happened in
September and October as a reason for
why it has to go lower, I want to just
say that you could be right. Like, I am
not against that outcome, but I want to
caution people into putting too much
faith in it because there are plenty of
examples where a higher low is formed in
September-October rather than a lower
low, okay? And gold already dropped
about 30%, right? So,
you know, if it wants to put in a lower
low, I I guess you're basically just
kind of like backtesting. But even then,
I I still think it it could in fact be a
higher low. So, what I'm looking for
with gold
is to print that low,
I would say between
now and let's call it mid-October.
I don't think it's going to take until
mid-October, but sometime we should
start to see that that move come back.
So, it would look something like that
and then you sort of bounce out out of
like bounce out of it. That is my
assessment into
how gold is going to play out from here.
Now,
if gold is not at new all-time highs
by let's call it mid-2027,
then I might have to reassess my uh my
thoughts about being a local top. I do
not think that that that will be like
sort of like the long-term secular top.
I don't get the impression that it's the
same thing as what happened in 2011, but
if we are unable to if if gold is unable
to make an all-time high by mid-2027,
then I would start to get a little
skeptical. If you look at the 2011 move,
what happened back then is gold topped,
but then
about a year later, it still hadn't
taken out the highs.
We're currently only 8 months later. So,
I would like to give it a little bit
longer going into say mid-2027
before I would be willing to to to to
say, "Okay, the top is in." But until
that time, I think you have to give, in
my opinion, like I have to give 1974
comparison a chance. I have to give the
mid-term average comparison a chance.
Because if this just simply plays out
and we're back at the average, it
wouldn't be a new all-time high, but we
would be right back up at the highs.
And
I I And the other reason why I think
gold is struggling right now is because
of the dollar, right? So, the dollar is
I know you're like, "Well, the dollar's
not strong right now. What's he talking
about?"
I think it's going to be strong and and
that could be where I I'm I'm wrong, but
if you look at the dollar, it's at 98.6.
I think it's printing a higher low,
right? Like I I I think we're just kind
of repeating the same process where you
you form a low,
you rally, you come back down, and then
you move, right? Same thing, right? You
you So, the low, the rally,
come back down, and then go up. And then
the next one on the higher and the next
one, right? A low, you rally, you come
back down, and then you go up. Same
thing. A low, a rally, you come back
down, you then go up. Why would the
dollar go up?
Because inflation and because the Fed is
likely going to start raising rates
soon. So, I think the dollar is likely
going to go up.
And what's interesting is if you look at
the path of the dollar
in
2018,
okay? And again, this is the reason we
do this is because it was the same
president, right? The same president.
Obviously, the administration would
prefer the dollar to go down.
But you can see there was also a
correction in the dollar around this
time during Trump's first term.
It went down, but then in just a few
days,
sort of in the calendar year, it started
an aggressive move higher. You see that?
And so, I think gold is currently
sniffing that out. Like I think gold is
aware that the Fed is about to raise
rates and that the dollar is about to go
up.
And that's why it's weak. So, by the
time the dollar starts to actually go
up, the gold low might be in or be very
close to being in because markets price
this stuff in ahead of time. Like gold,
in my opinion, right now is pricing in a
future dollar rally that will go that
will take us
into the end of the year, okay?
That's what I think. And I I think the
the reason it hasn't happened yet
arguably a seasonality thing, but also
just simply because the market is
relatively unsure if we're going to get
a rate hike in the first place.
If we don't get a rate hike, the long
end of the yield curve is is going to
struggle to go back down. And I know
Treasury Secretary Besson's going to do
what he can do, but when you interfere
with markets like the way he wants to,
the markets will then just test your
resolve. They'll see how far he's
willing to go to suppress the long end.
Because when when you start intervening,
it usually just leads to more
intervention, not less. It just is the
the acknowledgement that hey, you have
to continue to to increase the bond
buybacks in order to keep the long the
long end of the yield curve down. The
best thing they could do
to suppress the long end would just
simply be to raise rates. And if they
raise rates, the dollar goes up. That's
the weakness that gold is sniffing out
right now. And by the time
we get to mid-September going into
mid-October, I think the the low is
likely in by that point. And again, it
it very well could be a higher low. I am
in the camp of it being a higher low.
But if it's a lower low, I don't think
it negates the overall thesis, right? It
could just be, you know, something
maybe the dollar goes up more than what
I'm expecting. I don't know, but I don't
really think it would negate the overall
thesis of what I'm trying to
communicate. So, those are my views on
gold. If you guys like the content, make
sure you subscribe, give the video a
thumbs up. Again, check out the sale on
ITC Premium. Link is in the description
below. Thank you guys for tuning in, and
I'll see you next time. Bye.